Your source for Orthodox books, podcasts, videos, and more.
We are ancient faith ministries.
He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall.
And he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise and
and celebrate with song.
the Lord of Spirits. 1st denoc. 48 verses 4 through 5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels,
demons, and saints. In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular
materialism, to see and to know reality as it truly is. What is this spiritual reality
like? How do we engage with it well? How do we permeate every day life with spiritual
Presence. Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung host this live Colin show focused on enchantment in creation.
The union of the scene and unseen as made by God and experienced by mankind
throughout history. Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening, giant killers, dragon slayers, defeaters of the Drow of the Underdark.
You're listening to the Lord of Spirits podcast. My co-host Father Stephen DeYoung,
the vein of
Bob goblins is with me straight from the swamp
Lafayette Louisiana and I'm father and a Stephen D. I've read that is Bane of the Bogomials
Oh, which would have been far more interesting. Are you have you ever taken? I don't know you'd have to ask them
Bogomials call in let us know how do you feel about
So if you even listen, yeah, are there any of those around there must be I mean this is a internet age
there's people cleaning all kinds of things I want us to have an
Eccling Car listener. That's what I really want. But I am in the Mayas, Pennsylvania,
perched precariously atop the arcane tower of podcasting, hovering dozens of stories
above a disused gateway to the underworld. And we are live. And if you are listening to us live,
you can call us to date five, five, two, three, seven, two, three, four, six. You can talk to us
and we're going to get your calls in second half of the show and Matroska Tudy, Trudy the Tank
character will be taking your cause.
And tonight I scarcely have any idea of what model
Drone is on, Father Steven has in store, but I think it's something to do with time and space again
So we're going full Hagellian this time around right the big question though is what is it all leading up to?
You never go full Hagle. Oh, okay. Never go full Hagle
Can you ever arrive at full Hagle thesis and synthesis and this is a little bit of process a little bit of process
Right, you know, maybe a little bit of you know divine human integration, you know, that's okay
but no.
not full-hagel, never.
Rookie mistake.
Oh, well, someone in the comments just said,
I'm not in a car, but grew up in it.
God bless you.
That is a amazing sound they make.
You.
Maybe we should have her name is McKenna,
according to YouTube.
Maybe we should have McKenna call in and give us a good
us a good hue for old time sick.
She could write about the sadness of leaving the group and call it human cry.
Wow.
Oh, man.
You know, there is a whole, there is a whole genre of Eckincar like CCM.
They don't call it CCM, I'm sure.
But like you can go on YouTube and they have songs about Mahanta, you know, it's unbelievably
corny.
So great.
Can you lose your salvation in Eckincar?
Ah, like if someone just come up and say, hey, you get off of my cloud.
Wow, good thing she's a former
heck.
Yeah, or what I'm not sure.
I know the the the mahontas called
the heck master.
See, we should do it.
And of course, we would never
never get away with it, but it'd be
so fun to do an episode about
heck and card.
Now I can immediately segue into
what the heck jokes write like.
Here you go.
Thanks.
Um, nice.
Yeah, but tonight, uh, I debated
briefly whether we should just
spend two hours rivering on
rather dazzling.
should be a member of the X-Men or should remain solo, but decided instead that yeah as you
pose there in your original question, how does it all end? Right. Where's everything headed?
And then also started to be thinking about television because we live in an era now where television
and sort of has like a through line, like television shows.
like they're kind of planned out for a certain length of time
and then they have like an actual ending.
Like podcasts never do.
Yeah, well, this podcast maybe.
That's exactly who knows where the end will come.
But yeah, I like what we were kids, right?
And like just a show went on until it got canceled, right?
They were just breaking out episodes.
And like the teenage kids from the show would be like
their 30s and they'd have like because
and Oliver show up to try and keep kids up the show is still living with mom and dad.
Yeah, we keep generational, right? And then, um, yeah, or, yeah,
and they never had an ending, right? Like they just went off the air when they got canceled.
Right. They just stopped just vanished, like, like Chuck Cunningham went upstairs, never
was seen again. There's no series finale. Yes, there's no. We will never know.
Um, yeah.
So, is that what life in the world is like?
That's what we're talking about today, which of those models is it more of a breaking
bad or more of a TJ Hooker?
Facts of life.
Is it or or facts of life?
Well, facts of life kept coming back.
That might be the basic thing about that show.
The George Clooney shows up and like, or is any facts of life been off?
What is he's one?
Speaking of CCN.
Lisa Welchle who played Blair she had a
bridge
very brief CCM career. Yeah. Hard to believe. Yeah. And then a bunch of the other stars
would have to do a lot of like TV movies. Aimed at women yet featuring women getting abused,
which is something I've also never understood why do all of these movies for women's channels
involve women getting abused. Yeah, although sometimes they get revenge. So that makes sense.
Here you go.
And then Kim Fields showed up on Fresh Prince of Bel Air in a late season.
Anyway, none of that is the topic.
The question is, right?
Where is everything headed?
So if people saw the title of the episode, they saw that we're sort of talking about progress.
But the idea of progress is dependent upon some other ideas.
Right.
In order to call something progress, you have to have some idea that there is a direction and a goal,
right, that destination that's being aimed at so that you can judge whether something is progress related to it.
And so, but progress then is sort of a subspecies of change.
Right, it's it's changed in a particular direction.
And so you had application things are getting
better. Right. Progress would be positive. Yeah. In some sense, change. Um,
so we did a couple episodes the end of last year, a whole year ago.
Oh, the end of, let's say which last year, 2023, 2024, 24.
That's all right. So a couple of months ago. Okay. Okay. But also last year, um,
Where we talked about...
about change and we focused in those episodes on continuity.
We focused on the idea that even though there's a parent change
in humanity and human relations and religion in particular
and Christianity in particular, particular,
that there is an underlying continuity,
the sort of under-girds that a parent change.
Then so we talked about we really stressed the idea that there's continuity
like throughout the scripture, right, from beginning to end. And we even went sort of before that.
We talked about how there's a continuity, there's a religious continuity going all the way back to,
you know, your primitive hunter-gatherers, like all the way back, obviously, to your first humans,
right? So we're focused on the continuity that tonight, we're going to talk more about the change,
right the things that change.
And how to understand that?
Because we take it for granted that the idea of continuity
and the idea of change are directly opposed to each other.
Continuity means no change.
And change means a lack of continuity.
And tonight we're going to argue that that's not necessarily
the case.
Also in a number of past episodes, here
Where were you?
going to start in a number of our past episodes. We've talked about, as exemplified by 19th century
Germans, the idea of sort of an evolutionary progress. Yeah. The idea that, you know, and going
with that in the case of the 19th century Germans and you know fill in whoever else.
19th century...
uh, folks in the British Empire, uh, late 20th century Americans, uh, you throw it
whoever else you want with this, uh, saw themselves as sort of the pinnacle of all human
everything, right?
Like all human achievement.
Yeah.
I mean, humans tend to do that.
Well, everything was leading up to that.
Well, you know, I don't think that's true.
See, we live in America.
And I think we assume this.
I don't think the people who...
lived in Lichtenstein or like Lichtenstein is the greatest country on earth.
That I'll give.
But like Babylon, like Babylon side self as yes, the, no, it's the empire.
At the time.
Yeah.
Right.
Like, but you know, Switzerland is walking around going, you know, greatest country on earth.
God's favorite people, Switzerland, the Swiss, you know, I just, I don't think that's
their thing.
Switzerland and biblical prophecy.
Yeah.
Like not they're vibe.
Um.
And so, you know, I think most of our listeners,
and I think most serious Christians who are even vaguely traditional,
aren't prone to deliberately going down that road.
Right.
We may get sucked into it, you know, patriotism and nationalistic fervor and things.
We may get sucked into a little bit of that kind of thinking sometimes.
But that's not really
where we're at, most serious, even vaguely traditional Christians are not going full
haggle. But there is sort of another version of this that we do more often fall prey to,
or at least there's a much greater potential for us to fall prey to it. And that's the
idea not so much that sort of
we wouldn't say we're at the pinnacle of all human history, all human history leads to us,
if someone pointed out really, you know, if we were saying something along those lines,
we'd go, well, okay, yeah, right. But we do have this very firm idea, and this is often considered
by people to be a Christian idea. I'm going to argue it's not, right? But it's considered to be a Christian
an idea that there is to history.
to time, to the existence of this world, this creation, this cosmos, that there is a
teleology to it. And teleology, of course, comes from the Greek word, telos,
meaning purpose or end. Right. Which, yeah, literally means end, but
It means end of the sense of ends and means.
Yeah, I mean, we use end in the same way in English.
Like, that's the end of my day.
But also, I could say, well, this was my true end, you know.
Right. Right.
Yeah, there's the end of my day was midnight or there's the end of my day was accomplishing
all these tasks, right?
Right.
Reming the second one of those.
And this is one of famously, one of Aristotle's four causes.
is the final
because the purpose for which something is made, something's purpose.
So tied in with this idea of teleology, this idea of there being a goal,
that all of history, all of time, space, this causes this world as moving toward a goal,
is very much then tied in with the concept of purpose, and that purpose can often be tied in with our
ideas of meaning, right? That purpose then, so I might say, is what gives meaning to various things.
So sometimes this is laid out, right? When it's when it's talked about. And when it's attributed to
Christianity, or to quote unquote the Judeo-Christian tradition, whatever that is,
is
is in terms of philosophy of history.
And this is going to sound very crude,
but I can show you plenty of books, history books and philosophy history books
from like the 1960s that present this exactly this way,
which is that, you know, pre outside of Judaism and Christianity
or outside of bib-
religion. Right. They will say that ancient people had a cyclical view of time. Yeah. Yeah.
That that time in the cosmos, the cosmos just kind of followed these cycles that repeated over
and over again, add infinitum, not going anywhere. Right. It's not necessarily aimed at anything.
Where is the
they will say Judaism and Christianity, biblical religion, argues that there is a beginning
to time and history at space of the universe, and then an ending.
And they will say, therefore, we're going to interrogate this a little, but they will
They will say, therefore, they will say, this is linear time.
That time space, the universe.
Everyone and everything in it are going from point A to point B.
There are a journey from point A to point B.
And therefore there is this teleology.
Right?
And so then
if you hold to that kind of view of history then the idea of progress is a natural outgrowth to it because
history, time, everything.
has this destination point, it's headed toward. If you're moving toward that destination,
that's progress. Yeah. Right. Otherwise, it's regress, right? If you're headed in the other direction,
right? Away from it. Now, it is true. It is true that in order to have a sense of teleology like
this you do kind of need to have it's difficult to have it.
without having a beginning and an end.
Yeah, of course.
Right, if time is a flat circle,
then it's very hard to argue
where it's progressing towards something.
Yeah.
Other than just going around in a circle, right?
But the fact that you have a beginning and an end,
this is what we're gonna be exploring more here,
is the fact that there's a beginning to time
into this universe.
of this world and this life and that there's an end to our life in this world and to this
world itself and this age, right? That is not necessarily mean that it is progressing
toward a particular point.
Yeah, I mean, like the piece of paper in my hand has a beginning and an end, but that doesn't
mean anything. It's just, yeah, it's a fact about it.
Right, right.
So it can mean...
Right. Like a book. It's a decent book. Right. Does it just start at some random point and end at some random point? Right. There is a.
There's a teleology to a book. There's a story that's being told. The narrative is progressing from point A to point B.
Right. Or if it's a nonfiction book.
Right, whatever it's describing, whatever it's laying out, right, you start at point A and you move to point A.
B in terms of laying out the whole case or the whole, all of the information in an orderly way, right?
But a rock, right, is finite, right?
But does not in and of itself, the rock does not in and of itself, right?
There's not a purpose signified by the fact that this rock is three inches in diameter
and this other rock is 4 inches in diameter.
Right.
So you can have a view of time in this world that is not cyclical, but that also isn't
sort of moment by moment day by day step by step making advances towards some endpoint.
We're getting to more what that means here now.
Now, and this may be a hard set,
like you may be here, we say that and be going,
what? Like, of course it does.
Right? Like we experience time in one direction. Right?
Like, yeah.
Not it all directions.
Like, obviously, you know, like today I did X, Y, Z,
that represents progress toward this goal I have.
Right? And.
Right. Well, and even like, even in the scripture
you've got.
for instance, the sense of progress towards the coming of the Messiah, right?
There's all these things that are kind of pointing in that direction.
Then finally, you get there.
Right.
Let's say, well, even there, but that's a good example.
Okay.
Yeah.
Well, that's why I'm offering it up, right?
It's like, yeah, that's a good example because there is a certain.
So at the fullness of time I go
means, bet around Christianity for a while. Right. We'll interpret that fullness of time to mean like
and you'll get lists of things sometimes. Well, this is a Roman Rhodes. And there's, you know,
the Greek language was spread all over the place and right, there'll be a list of things.
And it'll be like, okay, well, all each of these things, right? And if you really like dig into that
and what that entails, then it tells, for example, that Alexander the great, concrete most of the
the
world. Yeah, was like a step toward what was necessary for Jesus, the beside of
you born.
Edit to those things, right? But and I know I've said this before on the show, I
would interrogate that a little bit, right? Okay. Yeah. Yeah. I'm just
Because, for example, as the kind of thing that someone might
say, well, what about this? I mean, that's pretty straightforward, isn't it?
Right. Like the, but you know, that's kind of an apostereoory thing. Okay. You're, you're assuming,
you're assuming there were a bunch of things that had to fall into place in order for the Messiah to
be born. And then you're looking at when the Messiah was actually born and trying to figure out what
those things are based on that, right? But like, sure, Roman roads allowed for travel.
But if you do
waited another couple hundred years,
you would have had better boat technology.
Right.
You waited a couple thousand more years,
you'd have the internet.
Well, I don't know how well that's going, but.
Right, but you know what I mean, right?
Yeah, of course, of course.
Like, we need this technology,
we need the Greek language,
so that the gospel could be spread.
It's like, well, you know,
could have waited for, do a link.
Translate stuff out of Greek.
What if you can...
Yeah, right? Like like it sort of begs the question of like, well, but wait, could have it there
been things later that were even better at doing that, right? Arguably before the Bronze Age collapse,
right? Like so, yeah, when it talks about the fullness of time, when it says when the time was,
basically means when the time was right.
Yeah, yeah.
And then...
We're trying to sort of come in and read God's mind about why was that when the time was
right?
But yeah, so that's not necessarily the case.
That can be the moment Christ chose.
It's become incarnate.
It also implies that if you take that view, that if any of those things had gone differently,
that somehow Christ couldn't have been born.
Yeah, right.
The magic hadn't, you know,
the ingredients were all together.
And then our Calvinist friends
come creeping back in over their horizon,
like, yes, see?
So God had to control everything.
They rubbed their hands together
and twist their moustaches.
Yes, if one thing went differently,
right, it couldn't have been.
Um, but yeah, so we,
the way we experience time
and the way we experience our lives,
like we work toward goals.
Yeah, right?
And we and our parents and our children and animals and plants, right, are sort of born and then grow to maturity.
Yeah.
Or sprout and grow to maturity, right?
And so, this is getting at what Aristotle was talking about when he talked about a final cause, right?
The final cause of the acorn is the oak tree, right?
Like, it's...
This is what the wheel is all about.
It's, yeah, it's what it grows into.
Right now, of course then you also have to take an account Aristotle then had
You know, it's on generation and corruption right then after things reached that goal
It then withered and died because of course he had kind of a cyclical view of everything right
It's this cycle you go to maturity and then you decay
But maturity the kind of maturity we're talking about right
Is that...
necessarily the same thing is we're talking about like biological maturity right?
That's not the same thing as purpose. So if you run into a 15-year-old somewhere
who thinks you know life is meaningless and everything stinks they're
struggling to find a sense of purpose and you say to them well no you're growing
and your body is maturing and some day you'll be 30.
that's not going to answer their fundamental questions about the world, right? They're
going to ignore you and go back to listening to Silver Sun pickups and crying softly
themselves or whatever they do now. I'm old. But to really have this sense of purpose,
we have to understand what you're saying. What we're really saying, if we say that there
Where is this?
sort of teleology to the world. There's this purpose toward which the world is advancing.
We're saying that all of history, all of time has this sort of upward arc.
Now it doesn't have to be a straight line, right? It can look like one of those graphs,
you know, which I haven't seen all that much in real life, but like every cartoon I ever watched
that involved someone in a business, they would have that chart with sort of the jagged
up down line mostly going up right
These are third quarter profits that's what would turn it around so it's going down and they'd be like sad.
But you're saying that history of the world are on this upward trajectory.
And yeah, there's the little dips. There's the little right, but mostly it's on its way up.
Right. It's like Bitcoin.
Wow.
So, well I saw her and see people show up in the comments only.
No, I saw...
I saw somebody had posted this from like 2010.
Somebody had a video game tournament.
And like first prize was like $250.
And second prize was like $100.
And third prize was like $50.
Fourth through sixth prize was they gave you 15 Bitcoin.
Wow.
He has exactly.
the guys who lost them.
video game tournament are down millionaires, right?
Um, if they kept it, actually, I think I thought out like right before it started
soaring, you know, because that was back when they had like physical Bitcoin.
But anyway, but so that, you know, one of those charts, right?
And you're saying human history is that.
So you can see you start out trying to say, oh, well, no.
Yeah, I'm a Christian.
So I think history is linear and it's...
It's leading somewhere and going somewhere.
And, but then when you start thinking about that chart,
you're like, oh man, I'm getting perilously close
to going full-hagel, right?
Like, this isn't that dissimilar an idea, right?
And that's the apartment in the sky.
Yeah.
And part of where the rubber meets the road on this, right?
the road on this, right, is...
is our view of sort of, well, we'll get,
put, let me put a pin in that.
We'll get into that later.
But so, as I said, especially in sort of mid to late 20th century sources on philosophy of history and stuff,
This kind of thing is presented as a result
of like Christianity. Like this is Christian thinking. Yeah. Yeah. Over against pagan thinking, right?
And I'm going to argue I don't think it actually is. I'm going to argue that actual Christianity,
traditional Christianity, historic Christianity does not actually give you that view
history. That history is this long arc progressing toward this goal where
each generation is making more and more progress toward that goal.
Whenever we want to call that goal, the kingdom of God on earth, right?
Something that has to be achieved or accomplished order for Christ to return,
sort of in parallel to this idea that there were things that had to happen for him to be born in the first place.
Of course, people got that now.
They're like all these conditions have to be in place, you know, especially if it hasn't
Do you want to do with the modern state of Israel?
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, I mean I really is yeah, yeah, it's
Yeah
It will be interesting. I don't know what'll happen to the rest of my life or how long the rest of my life will be
but
It'll be interesting to see
There could be a a
great disappointment of a whole new level
I'm not typically what happens in the Middle East.
There's of our dispensationalist friends.
Yeah, yeah.
But yeah.
And so I would argue that that's not really
a product of Christianity.
What that is is it's a product of what happens when you
take Christianity and you strip away the religion part.
You strip away the God.
Mmm, mmm, so...
So instead of the kingdom of God being something that sort of intrudes into this age and this
world, the kingdom of God is this goal that we achieve within this world.
Yeah, I mean, I think like there's a kind of utopianism that exists, you know, both within
the kind of secular or whatever, what that means.
World view that's anti-religion.
is explicitly anti-religious.
But then also frankly, I think this exists
within people who are religious on their face,
but function as though God is not present.
Like for instance, the book...
Or at least back like he doesn't intervene regularly.
Yeah, yeah, especially like the people
that are mutual friend Dr. Jenkins refers to as God's older brother.
Those who need to go out and fight all his heart,
just
his battles. You know, on that count, and this is just a brief aside. But it's a recent
forays into reading witch hunting material of the 17th century. I discovered that there
was apparently a bask witch who the French uncovered who claimed to be God's nephew.
Nice, nice, which is interesting because that you know
like I thought, is this implying a kind of humility?
Like he's not claiming to be the son of God.
He's just like God's sisters kid.
Yeah. Yeah.
You know, somewhat relatedly, although much brighter,
I know of at least a tradition in the Middle East
where women who are infertile who go
and pray to the Virgin Mary and ask for children
and then miraculously have children,
that those children are sometimes referred to as brothers,
Jesus is brothers and sisters.
In fact, one of my, I think it's my father-in-law's uncles, that's how he's known, is Jesus's brother.
Because he's the result of that sort of prayer. So, there is, yeah, nephew is interesting though,
yeah, like there's a whole bunch of things implied there, right? It doesn't certainly make sense.
I don't know, I don't know. But anyway, yeah, yeah, as you were saying, this is something that
God's older brother could pull in.
Yeah. Yeah, and so you get, appreciate any sort of stripped of the divine.
Where God sort of does an intrude.
And this even includes, this includes, you know,
roving bands of post millennialist,
who, you know, even if they live in Moscow, Idaho,
I still picture as sort of a
pock-aliptic
are warlords. Don't listen, what is best in life? Sorry. But it's so you can kind of strip
away the divine or you could go full haggle, right? You can collapse the divine into the creation
right into this world of this creation. Yeah. So that God is sort of, it's not that God is
completely separate.
from it, it's that he's completely in it all the time and sort of he's developing too,
right?
Yeah.
And the two are coming together, right?
So the question sort of comes down to, this is where we're going to end this first half,
right?
Hey!
that there is an end of history, right, in the sense of purpose.
What do you, what do you mean by that, right?
Or what is that purpose? What would you do, do you posit that is?
And there are some, there have been some suggestions, right?
So there's a book, The End of History by Francis Fukuyama,
that's kind of famous slash infamous.
Where...
he argued that history ended when communism collapsed, when the Soviet bloc collapsed essentially.
Because he was a hagelian of a type, I would say he was a dialectical materialist of a sort.
You know, I don't want to, I'm not saying he's a full blown Marxist, but...
But his idea was that what causes history to progress and the world to progress and change is
this sort of
thesis antithesis thing, right, which is not haggle but a
lot of hegelian types have views that
roughly worked that way. And so for him, for example, what was causing 20th century history to progress in the world
world. You just have that world history. And before
was this dialectical relationship between Western capitalism and Eastern
block communism. Right, they presented these two in some ways opposed alternatives,
them bashing against each other was what was moving things. Forward, Soviet
blocks collapses, pretty much the whole world becomes, you know, like capitalist
neoliberal paradise or hellscape.
depending on your point of view. And so history's over. There's nowhere to go
anymore. Nobody can think of any alternatives. This is just it, right? So most
most folks I would wager who are listeners to this show would not propose that
because that's not the view of history. They're not into the whole dialectical
thing. What the kind that comes into Christianity is more the idea...
that this world, this creation, history is going to achieve some kind of final form.
Right.
This isn't even its final form, but I call it.
There is one.
And that could take a wide range, right?
That could be like a post millennialist.
That could be like the kingdom of God on Earth.
And some forms of religious Judaism, that's a
essentially their end game, right?
They think the Messiah comes into this world
and basically just this world is transformed,
it becomes really cool.
That's sort of process wise.
But this could also be completely atheistic.
I mean, this could be like technocratic, right?
This could be like, oh, well, we use AI and computers
to like recreate everyone who's ever lived
in the great computer at the end of the,
you know, things.
or you can go all kinds of weird.
A robotic police force now, everything will be great.
Yeah, technocratic simulation theory stuff, you can do that.
You can just in general say, hey, you know,
just be a straight like progressive liberal type
and just be like, hey, you know,
more and more every day, people are realizing,
you know, the brotherhood of all of humanity
and you know, the age of experience.
You can finish stripping away these trappings of religion
and
nationalism and all these things and someday the whole world will be one and hold hands and buy each other a coke and
live in perfect harmony
uh
I didn't think we were going there but here we are yeah
Apparently you still have neoliberal capitalism because you still have to buy the coke um yes
But
Well, it's just not $50 a bottle like it is and uh that's true the future too low low price um
Yeah.
But it's all that there's going to be this sort of fun. But that final form, this is different than
the idea what we talk about in the church in the Nicene Creed, where we talk about the world to come.
Yeah, it's okay. Because this is the world to come is just this world
after having achieved certain things. Yeah. And that we make concrete progress day by day
in changing this into
that. Yeah, it graduates. As opposed to what is actually the traditional Christian view
and which was the view of the coming of the Messiah and Second Temple Judaism by and large,
which is that for us Christ's return where we stand now is going to be an intrusion.
It's going to be an interruption.
Like a thief in the night.
Like a thief in the night, or as in the days of Noah, people will be being married and
given in marriage, right?
I'm focused on what that means.
Right?
In the days of Noah, there was someone who got married the day before the rain started.
Yep.
There was somebody who had a baby, a new baby, a day before the rain started.
Right?
And then there is this interruption and that that can come at any time.
Right. That's the traditional. That's the traditional Christian. It's not something that humanity achieves. It's something that God visits upon us. Right. And that's why we've talked about this a little bit before on the show, but that's why this idea that like.
The Apostles all thought Jesus was going to come in their lifetimes and then they had
a sort of rearrange all their theology when he didn't.
Right?
This is where that falls apart.
because they thought it was going to be an interruption. Right. They didn't think there
were some set number of things that needed to happen and then boom. Yeah. After all, no
man knows the day or the hour. Right. Right. Yeah. Or the month or the year. Right. We have
to specify. It's definitely not easy. 44 there. Yeah. All right. Well, that's the first half
for this episode of the Laura Spirits Podcasts. We'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of
Spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
The centuries after the Protestant Reformation brought about a radical reinterpretation
of the epistles of Saint Paul.
Disconnected from any...
historical reality.
The Paul operated during his entire life as a faithful Pharisee within the Roman Jewish
world.
In St. Paul the Pharisee, Jewish Apostle to all nations, Father Stephen D. Young surveyes
Paul's life in writings, interpreting them within the holy tradition of the Orthodox
Church.
This survey is followed by D. Young's interpretive translation of St. Paul's Epistles,
which deliberately avoids overly familiar terminology.
using words and ideas.
grounded in 1st century Judaism.
DeYoung hopes to unsettle commonly held notions and help the reader reassess St. Paul in his
historical context.
Available now at store.enginefaith.com.
Again, that is store.enginefaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question call now at 855-237-23.
46. That's 855 AF radio.
Thanks, boys, to Steve. Welcome back, everybody.
Second half of this episode of the Lord of Spirits podcast,
we're talking about time.
Once again, kind of, which is to keep cycling back to it
because after all this podcast isn't leading to it anywhere
in particular.
No.
It's just going to someday be.
It's going to suddenly end.
That's right.
It's a leader, probably, yet.
We love to leave people on edge,
on the edge of your screen.
it's just to win exactly this podcast is good to add we may not announce it you know we might
announce it like suddenly and you will everyone would be talking about it and you will not have
listened to the episode yet. We may announce it after the fact we may not retroactively we may say
three episodes ago is the last episode just to confuse you and then finally I will get a lot of
hate mail. Let me just get a little I get a decent amount. We they had the commercial for my book by
by the way and I have to say that that book is now
battle tested. Oh yeah? Because when was it? Somebody brought into combat? Two nights ago,
in the middle of the night, I spent three hours arguing with intelligent Jewish people about St. Paul.
Oh, I thought you were going to say like in the middle of the night you picked up your
author copy and had a smash a spider with it or something like that. No, no, it's like 11 pm to 2 am.
Yeah.
Is this on the YouTube's with the result of the two?
our session was on a live stream in the middle of the night. Yeah, I know. So the things
you childless people do. It was a good time for me. I don't know about anybody else, but all right,
so since we're not going full-hagel, but you know, thesis and thesis. Well, so where we went in the
the first half was the idea that, right?
There is an end in the sense of ending.
There is an end of this world,
and then there's the world to come.
But that isn't an interruption.
That is not a goal toward which things are progressing
or being accomplished in order to bring it about.
And since that's not a goal towards which things
are progressing or which we're doing things to bring it about,
Um, that
That means that there can't be progress toward it.
So if you think that all of history is going to some final form and you think that final
form is liberal utopia then you could be doing things now to help bring that about.
If you're a post-millennialist, you could be doing things to try to bring that about.
if you're...
um...
a technocratic type. You know, you could be working on the AI that's going to someday return
everyone to life in the giant main frame of the future. Right. You could work toward that.
All I say and you can have a sense of well, there's progress toward that and then there's other
things that are regressive because they're leading away from that. Right. But if
Christ return is an interruption, then you don't have a sense of, well, we're progressing towards,
or I mean we're progressing in the sense that
like it's a minute closer now than it was a minute ago, like de facto, right?
So, but that's not how we usually use the term progress, right?
Right.
Not progress toward it as a goal.
Well, so that said, right?
Someone can come to us and say, well, okay, yeah, I agree. You're right.
There's no progress.
Right, there's no sense of progress. The world began at a
certain point. It's going to end at a certain point. That's going to be an
interruption. There's no progress. In fact, you know what? I've read me some
ecclesiasties because I don't like being happy.
I've been listening to Silver Sun pickups. Wow, that's a second reference to
that. So, you know, I, I, there is as it says, there's nothing new under the sun.
Just the same old stuff.
Right. Vanity of vanities. Yeah, same old stuff. And you know, there's no new ideas. There's no new thoughts that haven't been thought.
There's nothing new, right?
And this has produced this kind of idea or reactions against what we could call progressivism. And I'm not using progressivism here just in the political sense.
the political sense. Yeah, political progressiveness.
is a kind of this, but you know, Hagellianism is a kind of this, right? Any view that says that things are progressing toward a goal, reaction against that has typically been fallen into kinds of presentism.
And what we mean here in this case by these kinds of presentism are the idea that basically the world has always been the way it is now.
Yeah, I mean people say that obviously most people don't say that in the sense of like you know
We have the same technology we've always had but but often that you know well people have always been this way
Things are not getting worse, you know
Kids have always just respected their parents, you know
Every generation thinks that the next generation is more degenerate
You know all that basically see the world the same way we basically yeah theolithic hunter gatherers
as we basically, right?
Right.
right? Right. Right. And you know, well, obviously, Father Andrew and I could sit here
and phrase it in ways that no sane person would agree to, right? But let's give some examples,
least one of which is not super popular amongst portions of the audience, but sorry. You get
I feel like this is a thing like young earth creationism.
I feel like this is...
ham should be a friend of the show friend of the show can no no no
right in the show means they can come on oh does it yes and maybe I'm
thinking of the rest of history again where most of the friends the show
are dead yeah no barterman's the only friend of the show because he's the only
one who has the e-ticket he calls in he gets on the show all right anytime all
right at any point so pretty funny if Ken ham called in though
Oh.
Ah.
Younger creationism is a form of modernism.
Right, right.
As we've said before on the show, as we said before, irritating a lot of people, but it's true.
Why is it a modernism? Why is it a kind of presentism?
Because the underlying assumption is that the Torah, Genesis in particular,
is speaking to us in late 20th century scientific terms.
Right. And is this just young earth creationism? People who take a quote unquote day age view.
Also a modernism also making the same assumption. Right. The Genesis is speaking in late 20th century scientific terms.
The people who say that the text is teaching theistic evolution. Same thing. They're saying that the text of Genesis is speaking in late 20th century scientific terms.
all
of those and plenty of other related views are all forms of modernism because they're all
making this assumption that this text from Moses back at the Bronze Age is communicating
to us in 20th century scientific terms. We're going to get into this a little more deeply
later, but why wouldn't it be specifically 20th century scientific terms? Because we are
the end of history. Right.
who are the purpose of history, which is a certain irony.
Yes.
Right?
Because the folks who hold to this are trying to get away from the idea of
progress.
Yeah.
But it'd been kind of taken captive by the same idea.
Um, and this is true in general when you're when you take reactionary
positions, uh, you end up defining yourself by what you hate.
Yep.
And follow you right back into it.
Um,
But also, and again, I'm not gonna say who said it.
Father Andrew knows.
But I'm not gonna say here who said it.
Love it or it.
But one of the dumbest things I've ever heard in my life,
that's why I keep coming back to it.
The fella at a major European conference
who said that the bishops at the Council of Nicaea
should have voted to abolish slavery.
It's start, dum, dum, dum, dum, dum, dum.
So the, um, as if, and we've mentioned this on the show for as if, you know, the bishops
there could have just taken a democratic vote to completely transform the mode of production
for the global Roman economy.
Yeah.
I mean, bishops definitely have that authority.
Yes.
and could conceive of something.
to change it over to, right? We're going to abolish slavery and we're going to go to what?
Capitalism, socialism, fascism. There you go. An arco capitalism.
Yeah, an arco cap there you go. An arco capitalism.
There'll be whole patristic texts that start with you have two cows.
Yeah, first of all, you own your body.
Yeah.
So, right.
like what would they have replaced it with?
What alternative economic structure
did the bishops of the church
in the beginning of the four century have in their heads?
And where did they get it?
And why did they write about it?
That they could have voted and just installed, right?
This is ridiculous, right?
This is assuming that again,
They thought about things the way we did.
We do, right? And that they weren't living at a particular time in a particular place within an economy within particular things.
And of course there's an extension of this, right? Which is the argument that we commonly get from atheists and skeptics and those kind of folks who will say like the Bible should have abolished slavery.
right? Yeah. Right? Or the Bible should have taught, you know, equal
rights for women or nowadays, right?
Not in back in my day, but nowadays,
beverage farm remembers.
But nowadays, you know, you're usual panoply
of whatever the gender and sexuality nonsense is for this week.
I'm looking at you, Jen Alpha,
which is gender accelerationist.
Have you heard there's now Jen beta?
Like apparently that exists now.
Bye.
Well, that's sad, man.
I know, right?
Because those that apply that they're like,
get alphas like the dominant one.
I know.
Right.
I don't know.
I can't keep up.
We'll have to see how that all pans out.
I imagine there'll be a lot of us shaking our fists
and going kids these days.
Yeah.
Right, but somehow because we now know,
we know today that X, Y and Z is right.
It's current year.
Yeah, uh, that and we're right of course, and so that means if Bibles really from God then
Bibles should have taught this yeah
Right
Now at least one of those is valid right like abolishing slavery good thing
yes, right and
Equal right women. Yeah, I think how women find how we define that and how the treating women like their actual persons
Yes, right?
I think that's how that's all worked out.
Also, can be good thing.
It could be taken in some other weird directions too.
But, right.
But the fact that there's a valid point there
doesn't mean that these are ideas that
were thinkable at the time that these biblical texts were
written.
Yeah, I mean, as we put it now, those were not a thing.
Yeah.
there wasn't a way to refer to that, you know.
It just wasn't on the table.
Right. It's not like their walker go slavery is great. This is the best.
It's slavery was everywhere. Slavery was ubiquitous.
No one had an idea of another way to structure a labor economy without slavery
that would function. Yeah. Because it's not just a question of, well, we need slave labor.
It's also a question of how do you handle debt?
right? Because a lot of slavery was about dad. Right. And how do you handle
education and apprenticeship and it like I'll hold that's why that's why I've
said about council and I see it. You're talking about just abolishing slavery.
You're talking about completely remaking the economy of the whole world. Right?
Which you can't just do overnight. Now when you when you lay that out to our
atheists are skeptic.
friend who has advanced the previously said objections to you. They will say, well, okay,
yeah, you're saying that the people who wrote the Bible couldn't conceive of those things
yet, right? But you say God wrote the Bible. Checkmate Christian. Right. And so first part
of the answer to that is kind of...
Yeah, it's a divine human project.
Humans wrote the Bible.
Humans wrote it and the Holy Spirit guided it and inspired what they wrote.
That's what the church has always taught basically because that's what St. Peter says.
Yeah.
That's what the church has always taught.
So it's done.
that you know, fourth Ezra aside, it's not that you know,
St. Paul went into a trance or you know, lost 45 minutes of time.
And when he came to in front of him was the original copy of the
epistle to the Romans. Right? That we've never thought that's
what happened. Right? We never thought. Now, I think I've
I've mentioned other show before.
And I know because at the recent bringing this up is not to make fun of the person I'm talking about at all.
But just to to to point out how people from a certain background.
This idea of rubs them really badly the wrong way.
When I was first studying Greek in my undergrad.
And first reading the Greek New Testament.
Bye.
a friend of mine who was from what we would now call it wasn't really called that at the
time because this was again long ago and far away. What we would now call an IFB independent
fundamentalist Baptist kind of background. King James only. And I said well what's been
really interesting is seeing the different writing styles of the different authors. And
He got angry.
And it's this that I was wrong.
I was lying that that wasn't true.
Because for him if that was true, then that meant the Bible wasn't written by God.
Right, so I know when we say that, right, though the Bible was written by humans, right?
There's certain people from certain backgrounds who are probably going
right
What are you a liberal?
Um...
But again, that's not what what Chris Jesus or who talks right by humans who are guided
and inspired by the Holy Spirit and what they wrote in those particular texts, by the way.
Right.
Like every single thing.
Yeah.
If we find St. Paul's grocery list, like that's not inspired.
We're not adding it to the Bible.
Right.
Like there are plenty of other things that were written by some of those same authors.
lead over a fact.
that we no longer have and they wouldn't be added to the New Testament if we found them.
So, but so there's this this human element, right?
There is this human element.
And yes, it is hypothetically true.
It is hypothetically true that, you know, God could have explained particle physics to Moses on Mount Sinai.
Yeah, right. I would not say that that it would be impossible for God to do right
He didn't but I would again we don't restrain what God could do but he didn't do that
Right or string theory or
You know
The germ theory of disease or right there's any number of things that God could have told Moses about
I could have told St. Paulop.
about. Right? Or could have told you know, St. Matthew about right? There are plenty of
things, right? Christ himself to his disciples could have taught them about all kinds of things
science related had he wanted to. Right? But he didn't. Right? He didn't. And what he did,
what God does is he condescends and he reveals himself in terms that the people he's speaking
to will understand. Because there's another
hidden presupposition here in this God-wrote it thing. Right? And that's that when the skeptic or the
atheist or whoever says this, what they're really saying is the missing thing, right? You say God
wrote it. It doesn't say this that I believe. Therefore God didn't write it. That's sort of their
syllogism. The missing plank there, the missing arch.
argument is got agrees with me.
Yeah.
Well, and also, and also, you know, this idea of, of
perspacacity that like it should just be immediately
understandable to anyone who picks it up in translation.
Apparently.
Right.
Like, yeah, yeah, it should, yeah, you know, which, I mean,
which means that it doesn't need any, like what we've spent the last,
you know, for
half years doing is complete unnecessary because it doesn't need to be
conscious. Don't tell them. They'll stop listening. Oh, sorry.
Go everybody. Go on. Nothing to see here. You know, then it
just just pick it up and read it. You know, what why do you need
something else? Right. Yeah. Yeah. But so they have this idea
that right? Like so God holds to
21st century bourgeois liberal social value.
years. Yeah, we're out there. Right. Yeah. I don't want to believe in a God who doesn't agree
with me. Yeah. Or God comes down to that. The way the way things really work as God understands
them is 21st century science. Yeah. Although usually it's you know late 19th century science as
interpreted through memes. Well, yeah, yeah, but but that you know he'd be right with us and
This falls apart on their own principles, right?
They don't have to agree with us about anything.
Their own principle is what? They're progressives, right? They believe in this idea of progress,
that things are heading somewhere, right? Well, if there's progress, and if things are heading
somewhere, then I would assume, according to their own view, that in the 25th century,
25th century humans will look back at 21st century humans and say, oh, look at those
I'm sorry, I'm sorry.
and savages. Yeah, I mean just think of how we think of you know 16th 17th century human.
They'll look at our social values and say yeah how primitive, how horrible, how you know,
how hateful and spiteful they were and you know unenlightened, right? Well so if that's true,
then well hey, wouldn't God agree with those 25th century people rather than us 21st century
primitives. So from their own primacy.
It doesn't make any sense. Any sense for them to assume that God would agree with them.
Right? God would be in some sense in the future or represent that future,
that they're aspiring to.
He wouldn't be sort of in lockstep with them,
other than in sort of the very laymest versions of open theism.
Well, you might crack. Anyway.
I'm sorry.
Yeah.
And therefore, you know,
perversely, for the progressive to make that argument effectively,
they'd have to stop being a progressive and just argue,
we've arrived.
This is the final form.
This is the moment.
This is it.
This is now the singularity, right?
We're here.
Yeah.
And so what we're saying to counter to that, right, is,
No, God.
Neil himself got speaks to people, got communicates to people in terms they understand as a bronze age person as an iron age person as a Roman as a
Medieval peasant as a right on and on and on and on and on and on and we can go there. Yeah, and you know and you don't have to believe that people who lived in those earlier times and places were like dumber.
like, Dumber. They weren't. They were not Dumber.
But their whole thought structure was clearly quite different.
Based on what we can see of what they said, what they built, what they wrote.
Right.
Because the ideas, right, ideas are fundamentally tools.
You create ideas to solve problems, just like you create tools to solve problems.
Right, you have a need, I need to smash.
this open to get the food inside. So I find a rock. Right. And maybe if I find a sharp rock
that helps, so I find ways to sharpen rocks to help me, right? You develop technology, right?
It's tools, same thing with ideas. Right? Same thing with ideas. You come up with an idea at some point
in Lydia right they said you know we've got this great barter
economy going with caravans and everything, maybe if we had some kind of tokens, maybe
metal tokens, that we used as a means of exchange that would facilitate this process
and make it more efficient.
And lo and behold, we now have currency.
The idea of currency comes up.
But currency doesn't get invented in the Neolithic period because there's no need for it.
That tool isn't needed.
So, it's not that there was some change in humans and they got smarter so that they could
come up with the idea of currency.
It's that they found themselves in a new situation where they had a problem that could be resolved
by this tool and so they come up with the tool.
But we now, right, we're now living in a different world where we have different ideas and different
tools and rev-
of God that we have in scriptures or the church fathers or in the church councils or on and on and on is
And mashed in all of these different historical contexts
before us and so this is why
Christian ministry and teaching and every age has always involved
Recontextualization
Yeah, right taking what is communicated in that other context and
and now reapplying it to our current context hence
preaching. Yeah, I mean, you know, which ironically the vast majority of Christians who believe in the
perspicacity of the Bible have sermons. Like why do you just have, they're kind of long and in depth.
Right. Like why did you just have literacy classes to make sure everyone can read and then just hand out
Bible? Yeah, rather than 45 minute, yeah, explanations of yeah. Yeah. And but this is also this is
what most of the patristic literature we have is.
It's essentially homiletic.
Yeah, it's contextual.
It's the letters.
Applications in particular context to particular people,
times and places, which means that just like the scripture,
it needs to be contextualized for modern applications as well.
There's good ways to do that.
There's bad ways to do that, which we've talked about all that continuity,
which is the good ways.
Right.
You know, at-
Deadhead. Yeah, Saint Paul writes Galatians because in the region of Galatia, there are people showing up in churches trying to get non-Jewish Christians to be circumcised.
Okay, that's not a problem I have faced here in my parish in Lafayette, Louisiana. No one, no Jewish people have shown up in my parish trying to get people to be circumcised.
Oh, okay, so does that mean? Okay, well, I guess I don't have to worry about Galatians.
I guess that is no relevance whatsoever.
To buy people right
But it also doesn't mean so you can go the other way and say oh, okay, so that's not really what St Paul is talking about
He's talking about a spiritual thing and try to do some weird spiritualized thing neither of those things right St Paul is talking about that
He's addressing that actual problem that actually existed at that time
But I could take what he taught and how he addressed and how he approached and how he resolved that problem and
and I can apply
that, right? I could apply that because we believe that was inspired by the Holy Spirit,
the way he did that. I could then apply that to different sorts of problems,
ostensibly, different sorts of problems, different things that are going on in my parish.
Right? And recontextualize that, right? Into this new context, right? Even though this new
context as this whole different set of ideas.
that looks very different, looks like externally at least, looks like it's changed,
radically changed.
Yet these things still apply. And so when we get now into our third half,
we're going to be talking about those apparent changes.
Right? And what that means and what the middle way is between going full-hagel or
some kind of progressivism on the one hand and on the other kind of dumb, dumb
presentism. All right, with that bombshell we're going to take our second and final break and we
right back. Father Andrew Steven Daymak and Father Steven DeYoung will be back in a moment
to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 8558
The
People often complain that the divine liturgy is always the same, weak after weak, but every
ritual, praise, and action in the service has meaning and purpose.
Drawing in worshipers with its hymns and prayers and allowing ordinary people to leave the
world and enter heaven for a short time.
And the new book, Blessed is the Kingdom.
Father Stavros, Akraterianakis, a long-time parish priest offers reflections on the text of the Divine Liturgy of St. John Chrysostom to help readers learn to pray the liturgy and to understand and appreciate the mystery that unfolds each time it is celebrated.
Available now at store.enginefaith.com, again, that is store.enginefaith.com
We're back now with the Lord of Spirit.
the father Andrew Stephen Damick and father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome back and a happy new year to everybody.
Time marches on or does it?
For who the bell calls?
Anyway, go ahead.
Yeah, no, I would love to reset.
read a little John Dunne on the podcast.
I should read the flea. That would be a good one to read.
Yeah, we're talking about progress or lack thereof.
It's a little bit more of a metaphysical episode.
We promise it'll be much more fleshy next time.
Earthy.
Earthy. Earthy. There we go.
It'll be very earthy next time.
You'll just have to wonder what that means.
Oh, go ahead, tease him.
Okay, we're gonna talk about ritual
impurity bodily functions, bodily functions,
the secretions of all kinds, parental, parental
advisory is galore. Yeah, yeah. So but this time, it's
we're a little more ahead in the clouds. Yeah. So man,
we could we go back to that egghead stuff. This is getting
creepy.
But so where were we? Are we?
All kinds of places you didn't know you wanted to go on
It's a matter of yes I know.
And it's a problem with live radio as you can say whatever the heck you want and I have to delete it later.
Yeah, that's why you got to listen to the lives because half my jokes are gone by the time they're recording.
Just go know which half.
Yeah, yeah.
Since we haven't speaking of Hegel, I have to say, the movie does for auto.
The only thing I think that could have made that movie even better would have been if they had just had
out playing Hagle. He's basically playing Hagle. But if they just got ahead and said this is
George William Prader Kagle would have been sort of the chef's kiss on top of the movie. But you
haven't seen it of course. So no, and you never will. I don't know. So I will not. Despite many
scenic depictions of Romanian Orthodox life. I know. I know. I'm just too tenderhearted.
Where's my conscience has been seared like as by a hot iron? So it's right. No big deal.
People are sifting through it trying to find the metallic parts left over. Yeah.
Why are you afraid? So yeah, so we return again to the non-controversial subject of slavery, right?
So, we talked about...
In the second half, how expecting Bronze Age people or Jewish people living in the Roman Empire
or even bishops in the Christianizing Roman Empire to just instantly abolish slavery is dumb, right?
But the fact is, Christians eventually and all of them are
Christians in the history of the world did abolish slavery. The only societies of the
history of the world that have abolished slavery have been Christian ones.
Yeah, I mean I would probably add this wrinkle to that which is you know a lot of
non-Christian societies now have but I think it's probably under pressure from a
a world order that has
Like why for instance, is there not slavery in Japan?
You know, it's not a Christian nation.
Well, they've been Westernized, so they kind of had it thrust upon them.
Right. That's what I'm saying.
That's my thing by by the big Protestant nation, Empire, elephant in the room.
Christian, but they did not themselves.
abolished slavery. Okay. Okay. All right. There was no principle within Buddhism that led to them
abolishing slavery. Yeah. And Borshinto. Right. But we did. And we would say that's a good thing.
If you're one of those wackos on Twitter who doesn't think that was a good thing, just get out.
Just stop saying to the show. We're no. I know. Leave it. That's real. But here we are. Yeah.
But that was a good thing. That was the right thing to do. Right.
So, well, how do we explain that? Is that a change? Is that a development? Is that...
Because there are people who would phrase that this way.
They would be like, well, Christians sort of came to understand,
like there was a development of Christian understanding where they eventually sort of figured out
that they needed to abolish slavery.
Right.
Now part of that we've already talked about
the flawed basis of that in that that's kind of applying that like St. Paul could have or the
bishops that I see I could have but didn't because they didn't know they should yeah right and
like their moral conscience conscious that conscience evolved um which we've already talked about
why that's kind of bogus, but also we sort of have to, we have to understand and, and, and,
And this issue and other similar issues give us a window into sort of how this actually works.
Because as they were saying at the end of the last half, right, ideas co long at particular
times because of particular situations, right, they arise to address those situations.
Sort of what's the, how does that work?
What's the process by which that happens?
And so...
We have to start by looking at how the commandments of Scripture work.
And here's what I mean by that.
The Scriptures, even when we're talking about the Torah.
So you could say the Torah is kind of establishing the whole way of life, including the government,
the culture, all these things that we now split up.
The Torah is kind of establishing all of that for ancient Israel, right?
even in the Torah.
doesn't really describe and advocate particular structures.
Right? Like there's certainly based on the, the, the,
that we talked about this on the show way back of the log and go time in
Deuteronomy, the commandments regarding the king implies that
they're going to have a monarchy. Yeah. Right. But they're not
commanded to have a monarchy.
And they aren't giving commands.
to how precisely the king's court is supposed to work.
They're not given commands about how the economy is supposed to function.
Here is the economic system you shall use.
There's not, none of those structures are sort of laid out.
There's not even a family structure that's dictated.
In a sense that there have been episodes of the past where we've talked about and made these
contrast and
comparisons between the big, large extended families that existed in most
biblical cultures, compared to now that's been whittled down to like the nuclear
family. If that, right in our contemporary world, right? But neither of those are
like commanded by scripture, right? There's not commandments where God says,
thine uncle and thine aunt shall live with you into adulthood. If they are not
right now like there's not right those structures aren't like dictated by
scripture
That's not what the commandments are doing. They're not establishing these social and political and economic structures
But the commandments are aimed at
Is how humans are to act within and relate to those structures
Right, so
Israel is neither commanded to have slavery nor are they commanded not to have slavery
right. God of course knows that they will.
every culture in the world at the time did, right? But there are commandments given
about how slaves have to be treated, right? And about their release, right? Same thing
is true in the New Testament where we talk about slavery. Right? St. Paul neither
endorses slavery as a good thing, right? Nordesy commanded to be abolished. Again, as we said,
that's not a thing anyway.
Right. But he says, here's how you, you are a person who
wrote slaves. Here's how you have to act as a Christian. If you
are someone who is a slave, here's how you have to act as a
Christian who is an enslaved person. Yeah. How do you
operate within that? And it's significant piece of this also
is like the goal of the commandments of, you know, that God
gives are not actually, the goal is not to to create a
The difference.
society. Right. The goal is for human beings to be saved. Right. And you can absolutely become a saint
in any situation. Yes. And in slave purse, there are many enslaved people who became saints. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. The record tends, the record tends to show that people who have more difficult life
situations are more likely to become saints.
not that we're saying we should make life difficult for other people, but that tends
to be the case.
Yeah.
Women became saints without being socially and politically liberated.
Right.
That doesn't mean we shouldn't, you know, it doesn't mean it's good.
Just like, doesn't mean we shouldn't get rid of slavery.
The fact that slaves became saints, right?
Right.
But it doesn't mean that that doesn't stop you, right?
Yeah.
But here's what happens.
his father had to was just saying right
the commandments when we live by them, right?
When we keep them put it other way, when we follow the way of life,
when we live the way God has commanded us to live, right?
Those commandments that way of life is participatory.
We're participating in what God is doing in the world.
And that is transformational to us.
So an eye in whatever situation I'm in, right?
St. Paul also doesn't say like, oh,
Empire is bad. We're open party.
to be overthrown and replaced with some other four-brook government.
Right?
He talks about how to relate to the Empire.
But when I'm living that way in whatever my circumstances within what other structures
I find myself, but when I'm following Christ and living out that way, I am transformed
and as I'm transformed and other human persons around me are transformed.
Right?
By God.
This is what we call theosis.
We're all being transferred.
becoming like God, we're collectively being transformed. That transformation then causes
things that were previously unthinkable to us, like abolishing slavery, or women are equally
human. Those things that were previously unthinkable to us become thinkable, collectively.
other things.
used to be thinkable to us become unthinkable. So as the Roman Empire is transformed by Christianity,
Peter Asty becomes unthinkable. It was a societal institution that people praised and glorified
in the Greek and Roman worlds. Right? And by the time you get into the Christian era, they won't even
use the term petarasti, they use a different Greek
that means to filers of children, right?
That becomes unthinkable.
What had been a social institution, right?
And abolishing slavery,
say, Gregory of Nissa looking on PASCA
at the people in his congregation
who still own slaves and telling them,
you are a Christian, you have to release your slave.
That becomes thinkable.
That becomes an imperative.
So yes, St. Paul never says abolish slavery, but if a Christian is living the way St. Paul directed them and guided them to live,
the transformation produced by that is going to cause them eventually and collectively to abolish slavery.
Because there is this transformation.
it. And then at that point, you pass a law, right? At that point, the structure gets
changed. And why does the structure get changed? The structure gets changed because you have
to deal with the people who have not been transformed. Yeah.
Right? The people out there who haven't been transformed by Christ, we now have to change
the structure so that they do not continue in the thing that is unthinkable to us now that
stole her
remains thinkable to them. Right. That's after the fact. And as we've talked about a lot
in the show, but not recently, we haven't really talked about, I don't feel like we've
I feel like early on in the show, we talked about this constantly and less so maybe now.
But humans are our participatory beings.
You are gonna...
you gotta serve somebody, right?
You're gonna participate in a spirit or a spirit.
Even if you don't believe spirits exist.
Yeah, because, you know, I'm trying to think
of the best way to put it.
Like we're not naked Cartesian souls with, you know,
soul bubbles around us.
Like you're gonna, you're gonna be involved.
There's no way to not be involved.
I was just thinking earlier today, actually earlier this evening about the spirit of Florida
man.
Think of how many people participate in Florida man.
On everybody's birthday, there are several.
Right?
Yeah, yeah.
And so the Holy Spirit, as we're promised by Christ, will lead us into all truth.
So what that means is what we're really describing tonight, now in this third...
right? But the Holy Spirit is not the only spirit that humans participate in.
Yeah. And whatever spirit you participate in, that's going to transform you. In one direction or
another. Good or bad, never indifferent. Yeah. And so if you're being transformed by the Holy
Spirit, you're going to be led into all truth in the sense that all of the truth will become
thinkable to you it will make sense to you.
I know we've used this example before on the show, but as an Orthodox priest, as a pastor
of a parish, I see this happen all the time with the choirs who come from a background
that's very different than, shall we say, the Orthodox church, right?
And so things like going and kissing an icon is like big time, ebgb's, right?
That's weird, that's borderline.
idolatrous, whatever they may think, or these things about the Theratokos.
I don't know about that, right?
Or asking the saints for their prayers, weird.
Don't know about that.
But as they come and inquire and come to the church and begin to worship with us and begin
to kind of live in orthodox way of life, at some point it just clicks.
At some point, it just makes sense.
And that's because of this, right?
That's the very practical expression of what we're talking about right now.
Where these ideas, these things start to make sense, start to become thinkable through
this process of transformation.
But unfortunately, the opposite is true, right?
So a lot of things that became unthinkable.
within quote unquote,
Chris and them now that Chris
and them is dead and gone.
Sorry,
days fault guys.
It's done gone.
I mean,
Kierkegaard realized it was done gone.
That was like 200 years ago.
Now some of these things that had become
unthinkable or becoming thinkable again.
And we see them re-entruding into our society.
And we don't understand how anyone could support blah, blah, blah, blah.
Yeah.
Well, transformation happens, right?
And this is a transformation of the mind, right?
Be transformed by the renewing of your mind.
Remember that?
Well, this is in the other direction.
Yeah, because I mean I think
I think if we conceive of societal transformation not as moving either forward or backward
Right because you know which which implies this progressiveist
Or however you want to understand it, you know, but that implies that kind of linearity
Then it makes more sense like okay, we can move in this direction or that or you know east-west north south
You know up down whatever like there's all kinds of directions society can move in yes
Yeah, yeah
So that's one kind of right change, right?
Where we write something like where, you know,
change in terms of what's perceived as a change
in the church's teaching based on the fact
that there's been some societal change,
some change to societal structures
which the church is now addressing.
or is addressing differently than it did in another time period,
that's this transformational element, right, is what's really behind that.
And so, again, it's not a change. It's the natural result of, right.
So, it's not a change from St. Paul's teaching on slavery to abolish slavery.
It is the transformational natural result of St. Paul's team.
that produces the abolition of slavery. Right, so that's not a change. But the other place where
people often will want to say, well, here's your incontrovertible example of things changing, right, in
in the church. The Orthodox Church in particular, just the church or Christianity. And that is, well,
theology and what they really
mean by that is theological vocabulary. Yeah, right, particularly sort of vocabulary
surrounding the Holy Trinity or theological vocabulary surrounding Christology, right,
who Christ is. And they'll say, we'll see this is clearly a change or a development, right?
have gone from simple to more complex or
you have, right, in some sense there's been some progress here in understanding, right?
Yeah, and there's even like theories of the development of doctrine, which actually will
say that, you know, the church fathers understood doctrine more deeply, you know, than the
apostles, and then like the scholastics understood better than the church. You know, and so this
This idea...
that we care for. We've got a sensitive portion of our listeners who might realize you're
maybe talking about that. I know, but I'm just saying that that's the idea is that that understanding
deepens. Yes. You know, over time and what's brought out as evidence for this is as you said,
this development of vocabulary and this sort of stuff. Yeah. And it's really back. It's really
back to our hagel.
Yeah, that is backdoor hangar.
See, here's what you're really doing, right?
What you're really doing.
God is progressively revealing himself to humanity.
And in a way that, right, it's such a way that eventually,
there's sort of a merger, right?
So
I mean, let's not play pretend.
I don't think Cardinal Newman was a higalean.
Not right.
I think, in fact, quite the opposite.
I think he opposed those kind of views
and it opposing them kind of fell into the same kind
of ideas accidentally.
But ultimately, if there's progress,
that's progress towards a goal.
What is that goal some kind of ultimate full knowledge of God?
But if that progress is taking place in this world of this life then so does that
Fulness of the knowledge of God. Yeah, what what about the next life which is yeah the goal and so I say that that's why I say it's back to our
Higley and is um
You're on your way to collapsing the divine into history
Hmm
even though that's the I'll maybe the
is it what you set out to do?
Well, so we can't argue that no one would argue that no,
the church has never created new theological vocabulary.
Obviously, the church has.
Obviously.
Right.
It's just, yeah, lately obvious, new vocabulary.
But the question is, does that new vocabulary,
Does that new vocabulary, the development of new vocabulary?
necessitate or reveal or is it in and of itself a change?
Yeah, I think the best way to understand it is that it was developed for its time and
place to apply things for those people in that time and place.
That doesn't mean it doesn't get carried forward in new times and places where it can be applied
but it's not...
It's not like the capitals are going, wait a second, there's something that the gospel writers
left out, which we've got it. Yes, now we know. Yeah, yeah. And if we go into sort of how language
functions, we can get it a little more of that. Like, what are you doing when you create new
theological vocabulary. Like what are you actually doing?
Because as you just said, we're not saying that what they were doing was
Eureka, I now understand God in a way that no one before me has.
Right? No. That's not what they're doing.
What are they doing? It makes it so that, you know, it...
Like I'll give an example from my own experience.
Boy, this is a long time ago now, probably 30 years ago.
When I first got to university as an under...
graduate. I went and got a job at the local theater as you know,
full wealth, others, Stephen, that I did that. And I was asked right,
right when I was ready to work my first call, and I'm when I say
theater, by the way, boys and girls, I mean theater, not movie
theater.
How dare you?
In fact, I
stood above the cinema. Yes.
You walked to the board, sir.
And, you know, I-
I began working my first call and one of the supervisors on the call said, have you
done this kind of work before?
And I had done it in high school.
I had done community theater.
And so I thought, yeah, of course I know what I'm doing here.
And so he said, okay, great.
Could you just do this, this, this, this, this, this, this, and I didn't catch 80% of
what he said.
And so I had no idea how to interact with all the equipment that was around me based
on what he said.
And then...
And then he could see the look on my face that I was, you know, some 18, 19 year old
Git who thought he knew more than he did.
They said, okay.
And then he began teaching me the vocabulary that he was using.
And then I was able then to interact with this 3D world of theatrical equipment and
experience it in a way that was I could immediately grasp it.
Right, like the language bridge that gap for me so that I could make use of it, interact with it, and then, you know, make things with it.
And that's what allowed it's not that that 3D world suddenly became different.
But I saw it differently and I thought about it differently and I interacted with it differently.
You know, I didn't just see it any longer as okay, there's a series of things hanging from that.
I knew what each one of them was and how they functioned and how to use them and all that kind of stuff.
And so that's what the developer-
the language now it wasn't new vocabulary at that moment but it was new for me. It was
new for me. You know. And we've all had experiences like this where like you you gain a set of
vocabulary and you're able to connect with something in a way that you didn't before.
Right. Right. And yeah. And that's because as we as we've talked before and again this was
more probably early on in the show about the different the elements that influence sort
the phenomenological.
the world that we live in, right?
The world of our experience being language, music, art, and ritual, right?
Language is one of those.
Just one.
Right?
But so language is one of those, though.
So when we're dealing with language, language is shaping the way we experience and interact with the world around us.
Right?
It can't change, actually, change the world.
Sorry, modern progressive Americans.
Um, yeah, just because you use different nouns or pronouns or whatever doesn't alter the
thing. Yes, I can call this wall a hallway. I still can't walk through it. Yeah, right? I can
write it. That's it doesn't you can't change the underlying reality. You also can't change
other agents of the world. By agents I mean humans, animals, spirits, God.
himself obviously is the ultimate agent by be calling someone something else or referring
to them in a certain way or describing them in a certain way, that does not somehow enslave
them to my description or to my language. Right. It affects how I see them and how I interact
with them. Yeah. Right. But they remain free. Right. Yeah. I think, you know, I think sometimes
that we believe in man.
logic, almost. You know, like if you say the right words, that will alter reality.
Well, I mean, if you're Kenneth Copeland or Oprah, yes.
It's been a while since we took a shot at a word faith people that we need to do that.
Yeah. Now it can, it can alter again, it can alter your experience of the world, right?
experiential world in which you live. It can change that. Yeah.
radically. Yeah, you can feel deeply different and even see things differently. Right. You know,
but the objective, the objectivity of the world itself and the freedom of other agents in the
world is unaffected by it. Yeah. You can fantasize all you want that your favorite celebrity is in
love with you, they're not, they'll have you arrested. Right? That's right. So you must
That's what we're doing.
in my body.
Boarding all of our listeners in advance.
Yes.
For those of you who recently saw Steve Gutenberg on television and you know, relived a lot of
those 1980s admirations or whatever you had for him.
He's not into you.
He's just not.
Yes.
No matter how he times you show up at Dave Letterman's house, you are not his wife.
Yeah.
So that's not right.
And the way that we're going to call you back.
We have this idea that language can be used both positively and negatively,
but really most positive descriptions in language.
And this is especially true applied to God, but true in general, but especially true in applied to God.
Most positive descriptions end up being circular.
Right.
What here's what I mean by that.
So if I say, okay, God is all loving, that's a positive description.
I'm describing a quality he possesses, right?
But then you say.
to me, well, what does it mean to be all loving? What does it mean to truly be all loving?
The only answer I'm ever going to really be able to give is, well, that means to be like
God. So if I say God is all loving and to be all loving means to be like God, that's
a circle. Right. Not actually saying anything. Right. Right. Right. But, but that same
statement if we understand it in a negative sense, right?
Meaning God is all loving and I mean that in the sense that
Right, he doesn't hate
Right that his love is not weak and fickle like human love
Right in those negative senses now it's a true statement and it's substantively saying something
Yeah
But that's in a negative sense and
Most importantly, it's in a sense of distinguishing or differentiating
God
love from other things that are called love or distinguishing God from other things, right?
Or distinguishing God from things properly since God is not a thing, right? He's not a thing of
the world. And so these words and new vocabulary is a way of making new distinctions, right? And
and those distinctions can be important.
Those distinctions can rule things out.
Thank you.
can separate the truth of who God is from other lives about who God is, truth about who
Christ is, from other false conceptions of who God is by making these distinctions, right?
But the distinctions don't change who God is.
They don't redefine who God is.
Yeah, God is right.
Now they can affect your experience of God.
Absolutely.
is why heresy is bad for you.
Is bad and why we try to rule it out because it will affect your experience of God,
meaning it can affect the world you live in, it can affect your pursuit of salvation as a person.
It doesn't change who God is though.
And so the purpose of the language there's being used to make a distinction
and a distinction that is important to you and your experience of God, you and your relationship to God.
God, you and the working out of your salvation, right? But it is not a definition or redefinition
of who God is. And even if it were, it would have no effect on him, right? Of the actual
God who exists. And so there is not a change that is happening there. There is a distinction
that is being made. A different distinction that is being made. And that distinction is
idea that idea is a tool. Right? And so the church fathers at various points, right,
experience, hey, there is this problem. There are people who think of God as X Y Z or who
think of Christ as X Y Z. And maybe we're even teaching that to other people. This is having
a deleterious effect on them finding salvation because it's not true. It's not who God is.
And therefore, we will now come up with this idea. We will create this tool, this distinction,
which we will use to fix that problem, which we will use to correct that misapprehension,
and remove this obstacle to people working out their salvation, to people coming to know God more deeply.
We remove it by using this idea and this tool, and so the idea, the tool comes about
when the need for the tool arises, the need for the distinction arises.
But again, the new distinction, the new tool doesn't change reality.
Doesn't change who God was.
Doesn't change how salvation works.
Doesn't change how you as a human person are, but affects experience.
Yeah.
And final note, since we started out talking a little bit about this idea of the development
of doctrine.
This again, I mean, really on this, the ultimate answer this is refer back to the previous
two episodes that we started out reviewing on continuity, that if you think that, say, Isaiah,
God more deeply than Moses.
And Satan.
of Antioch, New God, more deeply than Isaiah. And St. John of Damascus, New God, more deeply than
St. Ignatius of Antioch, and St. John of Kronstadt, New God, more deeply than any of them, because
there was this progress over time. You have fundamentally misunderstood who God is and how he works.
But go back to those episodes about the continuity for more on that.
Yeah.
Yeah. Well, to wrap up here, I know a lot of people like, wow, this is really short. Yes,
it is. I get to go to bed a little bit earlier tonight. It's done.
It's what. Yay. But you know, one of the things that I wanted to kind of reconnect with is
this idea of functional atheism.
You know that...
that any kind of progressive view whether it's, you know, whether you're attaching a politics to it or, you know, theology or whatever,
it implies that God is not involved or as you said, Father, it kind of collapses God into history.
history itself becomes divine.
And I made a brief comment.
about those who like to function as you know God's older brother that they feel
that God needs to be defended all the time. And why I describe that as
functional atheism is that there's no apparent trust that God will is acting
in this world for the salvation of the people involved.
That's why, for instance, if you're arguing about theology
on the internet, you have to win.
And because what's at stake if you don't?
That's always a good question.
If you're arguing with somebody, or you're
going to confront somebody, is like, what exactly
is your plan here to win?
And what happens if you don't?
And why is it that you need to win this one?
And I know some people might say, oh, well, I'm doing it.
I'm doing it for the children, basically.
Well, the person that I'm talking with,
they're hopeless probably,
but all the people looking on, I'm doing this for them.
But I mean, that's not the only context
in which this kind of thing functions, right?
I had a priest one time, do one time tell me,
an experienced priest, a good holy man.
He said that a saint one time told him,
because this particular priest,
actually I'll just tell you,
If you check out my Orthodox engagement podcast.
and check out the interview I did with Father Nicholas Polly's.
He met multiple canonized saints so worth listening to that conversation because of all the
things he has to say.
But one of the saints that he met, I can't remember which one was now, he told him that
he needed to spend a lot more time praying, that his emphasis when people around him were
not doing what they should be doing is should be prayer and not pressure which
That's super hard, although in some ways actually way easier,
but it's hard, I'll say like as a parent, it's hard.
You know, if your children aren't going the right direction
or doesn't look like they're going the right direction,
it's hard, you know, not to pressure them, like do what you're supposed to do.
It's hard to pray for them really seriously.
That doesn't mean you shouldn't instruct them, you shouldn't correct them.
Um, um,
But if all you do is pressure them, then you have a problem.
And I think there's so much of our modern world
because of the way that we misunderstand what language is for,
that we think language like alters the world,
like it's magical.
Like there's a reason that word faith theology has become big,
especially in the last several decades, I think,
is because the way that we understand language now.
If we can pressure people,
shout people down, cancel people, whatever, then I don't know what, then what?
Some kind of utopia is going to arrive or maybe I'll just feel better by myself because
I shouted down the bad guys or whatever.
I don't know.
But again, it's functional atheism.
God is not involved.
So it's on me.
I'm the one.
I have, I'm the chosen one.
I'm the Messiah.
but I'm not and you're not.
And if there are things that God has told us to do, but if we're not accompanying it with prayer,
then we're not doing it right, because one of the greatest commandments is to pray without
seizing.
You know, and so whatever situation we're entering into, particularly ones where people
around us are not doing what they should be doing, which by the way, that's B2, each one
of us is not doing what we should be doing.
But you know, one of the hardest things in the modern world is to be surrounded by people who are not doing what we want them to do, which of course in our minds is what they should be doing.
We have to really learn to pray for them and believe that God is at work in the midst of all these situations.
We have to, because if we don't, then we really are kind of functioning like atheists.
And atheists is not necessarily someone who doesn't believe in God.
there's a lot of people who believe in God over the history of humanity that have been called by
saints atheists and they didn't mean that they don't believe in God they mean they're without God
they're functioning without God because that's what the word in its most literal and original
sense means is someone who's without God. And so my you know my my charge for everyone especially
myself because I'm lacking in this, absolutely, is going with God.
Don't be an atheist.
Be a, I don't know, matathist.
I don't know what that might mean.
But yeah, I'm using it very literally.
Be with God.
Go in with God.
And believe that God is actually going to do much more
of what's needed than probably I think, you know,
I can accomplish what's needed.
That doesn't mean I'm not supposed to act.
I have to follow the commandments.
But it's not on me.
Like, I'm not the one who's going to bring about
in the world.
And in fact, bringing about a utopian world is not the goal of the Christian to begin with.
It doesn't mean that we shouldn't try to transform ourselves, our families, our communities,
and so forth.
But we do it by living the commandments and by doing what has been given into our responsibility
to do.
So that's one of my takeaways from this evening's conversation.
You heard it here first folks, Father Andrews created metathism.
You may have come up with a new one.
You may get a, a, a resty arc thing going.
That's a pretty simple term.
Someone must have come up with that word before me.
I'm sure and meant something else by it.
Yeah, who knows what they meant by it.
Yeah, right.
Yeah.
Um, but yeah, so really dovetailing off of where you ended up.
Um, Christianity.
the macro level and the micro level throughout, especially the latter part of the 20th century,
and the beginning of the 21st, has been far too devoted to social engineering.
At the macro level, I'm talking about political involvement.
the idea that we need to create these external structures of force.
They will compel people into certain ways of living or not doing certain things or doing
things in a certain way.
Some of which are legitimately Christian and some of which are not their cultural
and other things and we're confused.
At the micro level, that's like the example Father Andrew gave.
I need me to make sure it all costs that my kid.
you know, makes it through high school and probably college without having sex with anybody doing any drugs or drinking alcohol.
And when those things are approached at that micro level, there's plenty of other micro level examples too.
Um, in terms of how we want our family life to be and how we want our parish life to be and then political life, how we can see of the place where we live.
Um, at all.
of those we address it at the level of social engineering. Right. There is an end. There
is a purpose we have. Right. There and now, you know, the means are kind of highly
negotiable. You know, if to keep my kid from sleeping with their girlfriend or boyfriend
in high school, I have to tell them that they'll get 23 venereal diseases. And, you know,
XYZ other things that, yeah, I mean, technically aren't true, but that are really scary. If that's what works, let's do it, right.
And if we have to, you know,
tread over a few people's souls and drive people away from hearing the gospel from the church in order to force their external
Um, come.
compliance with certain elements of Christian morality at the political level so be it
The number one problem with that is how's that working out for you?
Which is badly
It doesn't work
But then secondly even if it did
It's not really accomplishing what we really want
to accomplish. Because what we really want to accomplish is, you know, if you're a parent
of kids, you want your kids to know Christ throughout their lives. That's what you really
want. Those other things are actually secondary to that. And you want your parish to be a
godly, thriving parish and your wife.
your family to be a godly,
rather than family.
And you wanna live in a place
surrounded by other people who are following Christ, right?
Or that at least,
makes it conducive for your follow Christ,
or at least leaves you free to follow Christ, right?
That's what we really want.
And you don't get that by this kind of external
social engineering by trying to force it, or cajol it, or use language to redefine it, or
salesmanship, right, with slogans, or using people's angers or baser impulses, inciting
those and exciting those to get them on your side.
The only way you get there is day by day following Christ.
following the commandments as Father Andrew talked about, day by day being
transformed yourself.
And when you do that and you do that while getting around other people who are
doing the same thing, as we said that that forms out from you into a community
that's being transformed. And then at a larger and larger level. Right? It would be
better to live in a culture where abortion is on
thinkable than to live in a culture where abortion is outlawed.
Whether there's no abortion because nobody wants one.
Not one where there's no abortion because there are draconian punishments for having one.
Pick your social issue.
Pick your cultural issue.
Or we can go down to the micro level.
Right.
It would be better to have your kid.
not sleep with their boyfriend or girlfriend in high school because they
understand what love is and they understand human sexuality as God created it.
And so they wouldn't do that. It's better to have them not do it for that reason
than to have them not do it because they're scared they're gonna get a disease.
or their scared of teenage pregnancy.
Love is better than fear, 100% of the time.
Sorry, Machiavelli.
Right.
So, that's really what I think comes out of this,
and is the purpose of what we're talking about tonight.
Our purpose in the world is not to make progress,
not to build something.
and then have that thing we built last past our death. Our purpose in those worlds is to be transformed,
and to grow in the likeness of Christ, and to live in God's love. Not all alone, but with other people
around us. And when we do that, all of the things we're scared of, all of the things that we're
worried about, all of the things that we're tempted to try to engineer by force, those things all
all end up.
getting taken care of. When you
turns out when you seek the King
of God first these other things get
added unto you. About that. Yeah,
somebody told us that would happen.
Yeah. Yeah. So that's that's where I
think or at least I hope that
leaves us. Oh, man. All right. Well,
thank you very much for listening
everyone that's our chauffeur tonight.
If you didn't happen to call us
tonight, it was kind of a heavy one.
So probably why didn't we...
have too many calls. We still like to hear from you. You can email us at Lord of
Spirits at ancientfaith.com. You can message us our Facebook page. You can
leave us a voice mail at speakpipe.com slash Lord of Spirits. And if you have
basic questions about Orthodox Christianity or you need help to find a
parish to do all that 3D stuff head over to orthrocksintro.org. And join us
for a live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7pm
Eastern for Pacific. I watched the ripples change their size but never leave
the stream of warm impermanence.
You can follow our page, you can join our discussion group,
leave reviews and ratings in all the places,
and please share this show with one of your friends.
And finally, be sure to go to ancientfaith.com,
stroke support, and help make sure we and lots
of other AFR podcasters stay on the air.
So the days flow through my eyes, but still the days seem the same.
Thank you, good night, and may God bless you always.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits, with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young, a listener-supported presentation of ancient
faith radio.
And I beheld, and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne, and the beasts,
and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000, than thousands of thousands,
with a loud voice, worthy is the land that was slain.
receive power and riches and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11.